<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Database on Aman Goyal</title><link>https://goyal-aman.github.io/blog/database/</link><description>Recent content in Database on Aman Goyal</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-US</language><copyright>Copyright © 2025, Aman Goyal.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://goyal-aman.github.io/blog/database/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Understanding OLAP and OLTP</title><link>https://goyal-aman.github.io/understanding-olap-and-oltp/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://goyal-aman.github.io/understanding-olap-and-oltp/</guid><description>&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="tldr">TLDR;&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Any database falls into one of two category OLAP or OLTP — depending on the access pattern for which it is optimised&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="key-differences-olap-vs-oltp">Key differences: OLAP vs. OLTP&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The primary purpose of online analytical processing (OLAP) is to analyse aggregated data, while the primary purpose of online transaction processing (OLTP) is to process database transactions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You use OLAP systems to generate reports, perform complex data analysis, and identify trends. In contrast, you use OLTP systems to process orders, update inventory, and manage customer accounts.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Storing Values within Index</title><link>https://goyal-aman.github.io/storing-values-within-index/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://goyal-aman.github.io/storing-values-within-index/</guid><description>&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Relational databases can have one primary index and any number of secondary indexes. When queries uses indexes they use keys in the index to find values. There are two ways to have values&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Store actual row in index
Store reference to rows in index
Storing references to rows in index is a good when there are any secondary indexes. In this way when a value needs to be updated in row, it can be updated in one place and all the indexes can refer to that one value. Also transactional guarantees are easy to implement in this case. However, challenges may arrive when size of updated row is much larger then original row size that it cannot fit in its current heap location, in which case, row need to move to new location in heap. This requires either updating references in all secondary indexes to new location or leaving a forwarding pointer behind. In normal cases, however, hopping from indexes to heap for reads is too much of performance penalty.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>