<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>AWS on Aman Goyal</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/aws/</link>
    <description>Recent content in AWS on Aman Goyal</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2025, Aman Goyal.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/blog/aws/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Low-Cost, Zero-Ops Analytics at Scale</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/low-cost-zero-ops-analytics-at-scale/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/low-cost-zero-ops-analytics-at-scale/</guid>
      <description>One of the early challenges our product teams had was visibility — not having a clear view of how users interact with our product or what their experience looks like. This made it hard for them to plan what to improve next.&#xA;We’re a small, independent team within a fast-growing financial technology arm of a large enterprise exploring new initiatives. While we operate autonomously, all security standards and org-level policies still apply to us.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>[One Paper Later] On-demand Container Loading in AWS Lambda</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/one-paper-later-on-demand-container-loading-in-aws-lambda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/one-paper-later-on-demand-container-loading-in-aws-lambda/</guid>
      <description>You can also listen to AI generated discussion&#xA;Overview AWS released this paper On-demand Container Loading in AWS Lambda which discusses how they were able to scale their Lambda offering to support container images upto 10 GiB from originail 250 Mib.&#xA;Originally, users had to ZIP their code and upload it to S3 to run on Lambda. For each new invocation (especially after a cold start), AWS would spin up a new lightweight VM, pull the ZIP file, and execute it.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DocumentDB Load Balancing: A Key Learning from Our Load Testing</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/documentdb-load-balancing-a-key-learning-from-our-load-testing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/documentdb-load-balancing-a-key-learning-from-our-load-testing/</guid>
      <description>TLDR; API Gateway can provide caching, logging auth and load balancer distributes traffic between 2 or more servers for high-availability and horizontal scaling.&#xA;Both load balancer and Api gateways are used between web clients and web servers. But they have served different purpose, that is to say, they are not interchangeable.&#xA;Load Balancers Core function of load balancer is to distribute traffic. They receive traffic from web client’s and distribute them between 2 or more web servers.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
